66 percent of the [Usage] Panel found it unacceptable in 1988, 58 percent in 1999, and 48 percent in 2011." Ah, the Usage Panel, that trusted body of language authorities who is getting more lenient about this. Now, what I hope you're thinking right now is, "Wait, who's on the Usage Panel? And what should I do with their pronouncements?" If you look in the front matter of American Heritage Dictionaries, you can actually find the names of the people on the Usage Panel. But who looks at the front matter of dictionaries? There are about 200 people on the Usage Panel. They include academicians, journalists, creative writers. There's a Supreme Court justice on it and a few linguists. As of 2005, the list includes me. (Applause) Here's what we can do for you. We can give you a sense of the range of opinions about contested usage. That is and should be the extent of our authority. We are not a language academy. About once a year, I get a ballot that asks me about whether new uses, new pronunciations, new meanings, are acceptable. Now here's what I do to fill out the ballot. I listen to what other people are saying and writing. I do not listen to my own likes and dislikes about the English language. I will be honest with you: I do not like the word "impactful," but that is neither here nor there in terms of whether "impactful" is becoming common usage and becoming more acceptable in written prose. So to be responsible, what I do is go look at usage, which often involves going to look at online databases such as Google Books. Well, if you look for "impactful" in Google Books, here is what you find. Well, it sure looks like "impactful" is proving useful for a certain number of writers, and has become more and more useful over the last 20 years. Now, there are going to be changes that all of us don't like in the language. There are going to be changes where you think, "Really? Does the language have to change that way?" What I'm saying is, we should be less quick to decide that that change is terrible, we should be less quick to impose our likes and dislikes about words on other people, and we should be entirely reluctant to think that the English language is in trouble. It's not. It is rich and vibrant and filled with the creativity of the speakers who speak it. In retrospect, we think it's fascinating that the word "nice" used to mean silly, and that the word "decimate" used to mean to kill one in every 10. (Laughter) We think that Ben Franklin was being silly to worry about "notice" as a verb. Well, you know what? We're going to look pretty silly in a hundred years for worrying about "impact" as a verb and "invite" as a noun. The language is not going to change so fast that we can't keep up. Language just doesn't work that way. I hope that what you can do is find language change not worrisome but fun and fascinating, just the way dictionary editors do. I hope you can enjoy being part of the creativity that is continually remaking our language and keeping it robust. So how does a word get into a dictionary? It gets in because we use it and we keep using it, and dictionary editors are paying attention to us. If you're thinking, "But that lets all of us decide what words mean," I would say, "Yes it does, and it always has." Dictionaries are a wonderful guide and resource, but there is no objective dictionary authority out there that is the final arbiter about what words mean. If a community of speakers is using a word and knows what it means, it's real. That word might be slangy, that word might be informal, that word might be a word that you think is illogical or unnecessary, but that word that we're using, that word is real. Thank you. (Applause)
66% des panélistes la refusait en 1988, 58% en 1999 et 48% en 2011. Ah, le panel d'usagers, l'organisme de confiance des autorités linguistes qui fait preuve de souplesse. J'espère que vous vous dites : « Mais qui fait partie de ce panel ? » Et que faire de leurs décisions ? Dans les premières pages des American Heritage Dictionaries, vous pouvez trouver les noms des panélistes. Mais qui lit les premières pages ? Les panélistes sont environ 200. Parmi lesquels des académiciens, des journalistes et des écrivains. Il y a un juge de la Cour Suprême et quelques linguistes. Et en 2005, moi. (Applaudissements) Ce que nous pouvons faire pour vous, c'est vous donner une idée des avis divergents sur les usages des mots. Dans les limites de nos compétences. Nous ne sommes pas une académie linguistique. Une fois par an, je dois voter pour de nouveaux usages, de nouveaux sens ou prononciations. Pour m'aider à décider, j'observe ce que les gens disent et écrivent. Je ne me base pas sur ce que j'aime ou pas dans la langue anglaise. Je vais être honnête : je n'aime pas le mot « impactful ». Mais la question n'est pas de savoir si « impactful » fait maintenant partie du langage courant et peut être utilisé dans toute prose. Pour être scrupuleuse, je dois rechercher les usages, ce qui signifie consulter des bases de données sur le net comme Google Books. Et donc si vous y cherchez « impactful », voilà ce que vous trouverez. Il semblerait qu'« impactful » soit utilisé par un certain nombre d'écrivains, et ceci de plus en plus depuis les 20 dernières années. Maintenant certains des changements qui vont se produire vont nous déplaire. Des changements qui vous feront dire « Vraiment ? Faut-il que cela change comme cela ? » Ce que je dis, c'est que nous devrions être plus prudents avant de condamner un changement, avant d'imposer aux autres nos préférences en termes de mots, et surtout nous devons répugner à penser que la langue anglaise est en difficulté. Non. Elle est riche et vibrante et se nourrit de la créativité de ses usagers. Rétrospectivement, il est fascinant de constater qu'un utilise « nice » pour dire « bête » et « décimer » pour « tuer une personne sur 10 ». (Rires). On trouve stupide la crainte de Ben Franklin envers le verbe « notice ». Eh bien, vous savez quoi ? Nous paraîtrons un peu stupides dans 100 ans de nous être inquiétés du verbe « impact » et du nom « invite ». Le langage ne change pas si vite qu'on ne puisse pas s'adapter. Cela ne marche pas comme cela. Je voudrais que vous ne trouviez pas ces changements inquiétants mais drôles et fascinants comme le font les éditeurs. Je voudrais que vous mettiez votre créativité au service du langage et ainsi le rendiez plus fort. Donc comment un mot entre-t-il dans le dictionnaire ? Quand nous l'utilisons, que nous continuons de l'utiliser, et les éditeurs de dictionnaires observent cela. Si vous pensez « Alors, nous décidons tous du sens des mots ! », je répondrais, « oui exactement !» et c'est comme ça depuis toujours. Les dictionnaires sont d'une incroyable richesse mais il n'existe pas d'autorité objective qui puisse finalement décider du sens des mots. Si un groupe de gens utilise un mot et sait ce qu'il signifie, il existe. Ce peut être un mot d'argot, ou un terme informel, ce peut être un mot que vous trouvez illogique ou inutile, mais ce mot que vous utilisez, ce mot est réel. Merci. (Applaudissements)